Guide to the Boris Kaufman Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence, 1932-2004; Series II; 1.46; (4 boxes)
  - BORIS KAUFMAN CORRESPONDENCE
    - Société de production et d'exploitation du film, 1936-38 (Box 13, Folder 262)
    - Société de propogande technique artistique et commercial par le film, 1935 Mar 28 (Box 13, Folder 263)
    - Société française des films et cinématographes Eclair, 1949 May 18 (Box 14, Folder 264)
    - Société Vox Films, 1939 (Box 14, Folder 265)
    - Starr, Cecile, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 266)
    - Storck, Henri, 1960-69, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 267)
    - Surving, Elliot I., 1944-76 (Box 14, Folder 268)
    - Susskind, David, 1962 Aug 10 (Box 14, Folder 269)
    - Syndicat des techniciens de la production cinématographique, 1949, 1951 (Box 14, Folder 270)
    - Tarcali, Madeleine, 1966-69, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 271)
    - Tarcali, [Olga?], 1972, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 272)
    - Tarcali, Pierre, 1961-77, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 273)
    - Todd, ----, 1957 Nov 26 (Box 14, Folder 274)
    - "U" General, 1936 Feb 21 (Box 14, Folder 275)
    - United States. Army. Signal Corps, 1942 Mar (Box 14, Folder 276)
    - United States. Foreign Service, 1941 Nov 3 (Box 14, Folder 277)
    - United States. Immigration and Naturalization Service, 1941-42, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 278)
    - United States. Office of War Information, 1943-44 (Box 14, Folder 279)
    - United States. Selective Service System, 1942 Jul 2 (Box 14, Folder 280)
    - University of Southern California, 1973 Apr 19 (Box 14, Folder 281)
    - Vertov, Dziga, 1947, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 282)
    - Vigo, Jean, [1935?] Sep (Box 14, Folder 283)
    - Vigo, Luce, 1956-71, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 284)
    - Warner Bros.-Seven Arts
      See: Professional Papers, Bye Bye Braverman, Correspondence, Box 5, folder 73
    - Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.), 1971, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 285)
    - Wisconsin Center for Film and Theater Research, 1963, 1967 (Box 14, Folder 286)
    - Zinnemann, Fred, 1955 Mar 31 (Box 14, Folder 287)
    - First name only, 1944-73, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 288)
    - Unidentified, 1936-79, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 289)
    - Empty envelopes, 1940-78 (Box 14, Folder 290)
  - HELEN KAUFMAN CORRESPONDENCE
    - Borradaile, Christiane, 1981 Dec 10 (Box 14, Folder 291)
    - [Bramson?], Freda, 1980-83 (Box 14, Folder 292)
    - Comité du film ethnographique, 1981 Nov 20 (Box 14, Folder 293)
    - Cypkin, F., 1980-82 (Box 14, Folder 294)
    - Dalsimer, Janet, 1981 Nov 30 (Box 14, Folder 295)
    - Durant, Helen, 1979-82 (Box 14, Folder 296)
    - Foreign Exchange Control Board, 1942 (Box 14, Folder 297)
    - Halpern, Claudette, 1971-82 (Box 14, Folder 298)
    - Jamet, Ida, 1981 Sep 28 (Box 14, Folder 299)
    - Lumet, Sidney, 1982 Oct 28 (Box 14, Folder 300)
    - Pruginin, Lilit, 1980-81 (Box 14, Folder 301)
    - Read, Florence, 1965 Feb 28 (Box 14, Folder 302)
    - Rudnick, ----, 1941 (Box 14, Folder 303)
    - Starr, Cecile, 1981 Jan 5 (Box 14, Folder 304)
    - Storck, Henri, 1980 Dec 16 (Box 14, Folder 305)
    - Tabajovich, [Rebecca?], 1968 Jan 16 (Box 14, Folder 306)
    - Tarcali, Olga, 1978-82, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 307)
    - Tarcali, Pierre, 1980 Jul 7 (Box 14, Folder 308)
    - University of Wyoming, 1980 Sep 12 (Box 14, Folder 309)
    - Condolence letters, 1980 (Box 14, Folder 310)
      Includes letters from Elia Kazan and Luce Vigo
    - First name only, 1965-81, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 311)
    - Unidentified, 1980, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 312)
  - ANDRÉ KAUFMAN CORRESPONDENCE
    - Buchman, Dian Dincin (Box 15, Folder 313)
    - Kazan, Elia, 1983 Jun 16 (Box 15, Folder 314)
    - Mackay, John, 2004 Sep 24 (Box 15, Folder 315)
      Includes translations of two postcards from Dziga Vertov to Boris Kaufman dating from 1946 and 1947
    - Others, 1983, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 316)
  - THIRD PARTY CORRESPONDENCE
    - Beckwith, Frank to William Hussung, 1943 Sep 27 (Box 15, Folder 317)
    - Blackburn, Edward O. to "Charlie", 1955 Nov 21 (Box 15, Folder 318)
    - Consolidated Film Industries, Inc. to [Henwar Rodakiewicz], 1947 Oct 2 (Box 15, Folder 319)
    - Gimbel, Benedict to Columbia Broadcasting System, 1942 Feb 10 (Box 15, Folder 320)
    - Gimbel, Benedict to National Broadcasting Company, 1942 Feb 10 (Box 15, Folder 321)
    - Gimbel, Benedict to J. R. Poppele, 1942 Feb 10 (Box 15, Folder 322)
    - Paramount Pictures Inc. to Henwar Rodakiewicz, 1947 Sep 26 (Box 15, Folder 323)
    - [Surving, Elliot?] to Serge Kaufman, 1945 Feb 19 (Box 15, Folder 324)
    - Witt, Peter to Kurt Frangs Agency, 1957 Jun 25 (Box 15, Folder 325)
    - "Serge" to "cher papa", n.d. (Box 15, Folder 326)
- Writings, 1931-1994; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series III, Writings, is organized into two subseries: Writings of Boris Kaufman and Writings of Others.
  - WRITINGS OF BORIS KAUFMAN
    - ["A Propos de Nice..."], lecture, drafts, typescript and typescript carbon (Box 16, Folder 327)
    - "Film Making as an Art," article, drafts, holograph and typescript, corrected, galley proof, and reprint, Daedalus, 1959-60 (Box 16, Folder 328)
    - "Un génie lucide," article, printed version, Ciné-Club
      See: Other Material, Printed Ephemera, Clippings, Box 18, folder 367
    - "I Envy the Amateur," article, printed version, Popular Photography, 1956 Dec (Box 16, Folder 329)
    - ["I have been asked..."], lecture, draft, holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 330)
    - Research notes and reports relating to pictoscope, pictograph, and magigraph, typescript carbon, 1950 Mar 27 (Box 16, Folder 331)
    - "Working with Kazan," [lecture?], drafts, typescript, corrected, and typescript carbon, 1973 (Box 16, Folder 332)
    - Other writings, notes and drafts, holograph, corrected (Box 16, Folder 333)
  - WRITINGS OF OTHERS
    - Crafton, Donald
      - "Boris Kaufman: Shooting Vigo's Films," draft, interview, typescript photocopy, corrected, 1978 Jan (Box 16, Folder 334)
    - Durgnat, Raymond
      - "Man With a Movie Camera," book review, printed version, 1984 Oct (Box 16, Folder 335)
    - Kagan, Simon
      - "Entrevue avec Boris Kaufman," interview, draft, typescript, corrected, photocopy, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 336)
    - Kaufman, Mikhail
      - "An Interview," printed version, October, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 337)
    - Kazan, Elia
      - "The Director and the Public: A Symposium," printed version, Film Culture, 1955 (Box 16, Folder 338)
    - Knight, Arthur
      - "The History of Sex in Cinema," article, printed version, Playboy, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 339)
    - Mekas, Jonas
      - "Interview with Boris Kaufman," article, printed version, Film Culture, 1955 (Box 16, Folder 340)
    - Mills, Brian
      - "Jean Vigo: Anarchy, Surrealism and Optimisn in Zéro de conduite ," article, printed version, Cinema (Box 16, Folder 341)
    - Rouch, Jean
      - "The Camera and Man," article, printed version, photocopy (Box 16, Folder 342)
    - Simon, William G.
      - "The Films of Jean Vigo," dissertation, typescript photocopy, 1973 Oct (Box 16, Folder 343)
        Includes ANS, dated Feb 6, 1975, from Simon to Boris Kaufman
    - Starr, Cecile
      - "Boris Kaufman: Director of Cinematography," drafts, article, typescript copies, corrected (Box 16, Folder 344)
    - Tode, Thomas
      - "Un Soviétique escalade la Tour Eiffel: Dziga Vertov à Paris," article, printed version, Revue de la cinématheque, photocopy, 1994 (Box 16, Folder 345)
    - Vertov, Dziga
      - "The Factory of Facts and Other Writings," printed version, October, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 346)
    - Vigo, Jean
      - "Towards a Social Cinema," statement, typescript photocopy, 1931 (Box 16, Folder 347)
    - Unidentified
      - "Jazz," scenario, draft, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 348)
      - Untitled, tribute to Kaufman, draft, holograph, [ca. 1980] (Box 16, Folder 349)
- Other Papers, 1836-1981; Series IV; 1.46; (6 boxes)
  Series IV, Other Papers, is organzied into five subseries: Artwork, Helen Kaufman Papers, Photographs, Printed Ephemera, and Other Material.
  - ARTWORK
    - Drawings, 1955-67, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 350)
      Includes drawings by "Nebbia" and Brian Mills
    - Engravings, 1836, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 351)
  - HELEN KAUFMAN PAPERS
    - Certificate, 1980 Dec (Box 17, Folder 352)
    - Clippings and printed ephemera, 1981, n.d (Box 17, Folder 353)
    - Papers relating to "French years", 1937-40 (Box 17, Folder 354)
    - Passports, 1965-72 (Box 17, Folder 355)
  - PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Kaufman, Boris, 1954, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 356-357)
      Includes portraits by Hella Hammid, Aliza Auerbach, and Atelier von Behr
    - Kaufman, Boris with others, 1968-75, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 358)
      Includes letter from International Photographers of the Motion Picture Industries and photographs of Jean Vigo, Helen Kaufman, Eugene Shuftan, and Elliot Surving
    - Others, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 359)
      Includes photographs of Elia Kazan and Sophia Loren
    - Places, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 360)
  - PRINTED EPHEMERA
    - American Society of Cinematographers material, 1954-58, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 361)
    - Awards and commemorative material, 1951-79 (Box 17, Folder 362-364)
    - Brochures, programs and promotional material, 1935-81, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 365)
    - Business cards, n.d. (Box 17, Folder 366)
    - Clippings, 1937-81, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 367)
      Includes February 1949 issue of Ciné-Club, with articles by Boris Kaufman, Jean Vigo, Claude Aveline, Jean Painlevé, and others
    - Identity and membership cards, 1946-47 (Box 18, Folder 368)
    - Invitations, 1943-80, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 369)
    - Issue of Iskustvo Kino, 1957 (Box 18, Folder 370)
    - Journals mentioning Boris Kaufman, 1954-65 (Box 18, Folder 371-375)
    - Postcards, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 376)
    - Ticket stubs, 1946-57, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 377)
  - OTHER
    - Address books, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 378-381)
    - Address lists, 1964-66, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 382)
    - Awards and commemorative material, 1954, 1957 (Box 19, Folder 383-384)
    - Bates Secretary with telephone numbers and addresses (Box 19, Folder 385)
    - Bills and receipts, 1936-41, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 386)
    - Binder with "Movie Notes: Vigo Years", 1938, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 387-389)
    - Biographical information, 1955-80, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 390)
      Includes lists of films
    - Chaja Kaufman papers, 1941 (Box 19, Folder 391)
    - Completed forms, 1942-43 (Box 19, Folder 392)
    - Cut film, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 393)
    - Identity and membership cards, 1949, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 394)
      Includes photograph
    - List of Association Internationale des Documentaristes members, [1972?] (Box 19, Folder 395)
    - Lists of films, 1971 (Box 20, Folder 396)
    - Manuscript notes, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 397)
    - Medical records, 1941 Dec 24 (Box 20, Folder 398)
    - Military papers, 1940 (Box 20, Folder 399)
    - Notices of U.S. Civil Service Commission Offical Efficiency Rating, 1944-45 (Box 20, Folder 400)
    - Papers relating to "Paris years", 1938-41, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 401)
    - Passports, 1949-77 (Box 20, Folder 402)
    - Serge Kaufman papers, 1941 Dec 24 (Box 20, Folder 403)
    - Tiffen 52mm polarizer, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 404)
- Oversize, 1934-1974; 3.93; (3 boxes)
  Notes: The cut film in box 21 is stored separately in cold storage.
  - Baby Doll film boards (In Series I), [ca. 1956-57] (Box 21, Folder 405-416)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - L'Atalante photographs (In Series I), [ca. 1934] (Box 22, Folder 417)
  - Baby Doll photographs (In Series I), [1956] (Box 22, Folder 418)
  - The Brotherhood photographs (In Series I), [ca. 1968] (Box 22, Folder 419)
  - Film clippings (In Series I), n.d. (Box 22, Folder 420)
  - The Fugitive Kind photographs (In Series I), [ca. 1959] (Box 22, Folder 421)
  - The Pawnbroker photographs (In Series I), n.d. (Box 22, Folder 422)
  - The World of Henry Orient photographs (In Series I), 1968, n.d. (Box 22, Folder 423-424)
  - Zero de conduite clippings (In Series I), 1962 Jan 7 (Box 23, Folder 425)
  - Galley proof, with proofreaders' marks, for "Film Making as an Art" (In Series III), 1959 Oct 27 (Box 23, Folder 426)
  - Photographs of Boris Kaufman (In Series IV), n.d. (Box 23, Folder 427)
  - Clippings (In Series IV), 1934-74 (Box 23, Folder 428)
  - Commemorative certificate (In Series IV) (Box 23, Folder 429)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.42; (1 box)
  - Box 1, folder 3 (Box 24, Folder 430)
  - Box 1, folder 6 (Box 24, Folder 431)
  - Box 1, folder 7 (Box 24, Folder 432)
  - Box 5, folder 76 (Box 24, Folder 433)
  - Box 5, folder 78 (Box 24, Folder 434)
  - Box 6, folder 83 (Box 24, Folder 435)
  - Box 6, folder 92 (Box 24, Folder 436)
  - Box 7, folder 97 (Box 24, Folder 437)
  - Box 7, folders 105-107 (Box 24, Folder 438)
  - Box 7, folder 108 (Box 24, Folder 439)
  - Box 7, folder 109 (Box 24, Folder 440)
  - Box 8, folder 120 (Box 24, Folder 441)
  - Box 8, folder 123 (Box 24, Folder 442)
  - Box 9, folder 128 (Box 24, Folder 443)
  - Box 9, folder 130 (Box 24, Folder 444)
  - Box 9, folder 131 (Box 24, Folder 445)
  - Box 9, folder 135 (Box 24, Folder 446)
  - Box 10, folder 141 (Box 24, Folder 447)
  - Box 10, folder 148 (Box 24, Folder 448)
  - Box 10, folder 149 (Box 24, Folder 449)
  - Box 11, folder 160 (Box 24, Folder 450)
  - Box 11, folder 166 (Box 24, Folder 451)
  - Box 12, folder 169 (Box 24, Folder 452)
  - Box 12, folder 189 (Box 24, Folder 453)
  - Box 12, folder 203 (Box 24, Folder 454)
  - Box 12, folder 205 (Box 24, Folder 455)
  - Box 12, folder 206 (Box 24, Folder 456)
  - Box 12, folder 209 (Box 24, Folder 457)
  - Box 13, folder 213 (Box 24, Folder 458)
  - Box 13, fodler 222 (Box 24, Folder 459)
  - Box 13, folders 224-225 (Box 24, Folder 460)
  - Box 13, folder 226 (Box 24, Folder 461)
  - Box 13, folder 231 (Box 24, Folder 462)
  - Box 13, folder 232 (Box 24, Folder 463)
  - Box 13, folder 238 (Box 24, Folder 464)
  - Box 13, folder 245 (Box 24, Folder 465)
  - Box 13, folder 252 (Box 24, Folder 466)
  - Box 13, folder 255 (Box 24, Folder 467)
  - Box 14, folder 287 (Box 24, Folder 468)
  - Box 14, folder 289 (Box 24, Folder 469)
  - Box 14, folder 311 (Box 24, Folder 470)
  - Box 15, folder 317 (Box 24, Folder 471)
  - Box 16, folder 330 (Box 24, Folder 472)
  - Box 16, folder 331 (Box 24, Folder 473)
  - Box 16, folder 342 (Box 24, Folder 474)
  - Box 18, folder 367 (Box 24, Folder 475)
- Restricted Fragile Oversize, 1.67; (2 boxes)
  - All the Way Home clippings (In Series I) (Box 25, Folder 476)
  - Baby Doll clippings (In Series I), 1956 (Box 25, Folder 477)
  - The Brotherhood clippings (In Series I) (Box 25, Folder 478)
  - Fort Dolorès clippings (In Series I), 1939 (Box 25, Folder 479)
  - The Fugitive Kind clippings (In Series I), 1959-61, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 480)
  - The Group clippings (In Series I), 1965-66 (Box 25, Folder 481)
  - Long Day's Journey in to Night (In Series I), 1961-62, n.d. (Box 25, Folder 482)
  - On the Waterfront clippings (In Series I), 1954-55 (Box 25, Folder 483)
  - Patterns clippings (In Series I), 1956 Feb 12 (Box 25, Folder 484)
  - The Pawnbroker clippings (In Series I) (Box 25, Folder 485)
  - Splendor in the Grass clippings (In Series I) (Box 25, Folder 486)
  - Tell Me that You Love ME, Junie Moon clippings (In Series I), 1969 Sep (Box 25, Folder 487)
  - That Kind of Woman clippings (In Series I) (Box 25, Folder 488)
  - Twelve Angry Men clippings (In Series I), n.d. (Box 25, Folder 489)
  - Uptight clippings (In Series I), 1968 (Box 25, Folder 490)
  - Clippings (In Series IV), 1949 (Box 25, Folder 491)
  - Phonographic albums (Box 26 (Record album storage), Folder 492)